<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for punishing of such persons as live at high rates, and have no visible estate, profession or calling answerable thereunto.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1065_29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210931</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869679</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869679</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82394)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 159:E1065[29])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for punishing of such persons as live at high rates, and have no visible estate, profession or calling answerable thereunto.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, and John Field, Printers to His Highness,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gambling --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wealth --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169285:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>seal or coat of arms of the Commonwealth</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>AN ACT For puniſhing of ſuch Perſons as live at high Rates, and have no viſible Eſtate, Profeſſion or Calling anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas divers lewd and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Perſons in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, live at very high Rates and great Expences, having no viſible Eſtate, Profeſſion, or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (anſwerable thereunto) to maintain themſelves in their licentious, looſe and ungodly practiſes, do make it their Trade and Livelyhood to Cheat, Deboyſt, Cozen, and Deceive the young Gentry, and other the good People of this Commonwealth; Be it Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Highneſs the Lord Protector and this preſent Parliament, and the Authority thereof, That all and every Iuſtice of Peace, in any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169285:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
County, and all and every Iuſtice of Peace, Maior, or other head Officer, in any City, Burrough, or Town Corporate, ſhall, within their reſpective Limits, have power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, by Warrant under his or their hands and Seals, to ſend for every ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to require of him or them ſufficient Sureties, aſwell for his as their appearance at the next General Seſſions for the Peace, to be held in ſuch County, City, Burrough or Town Corporate, as for his or their good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing; And in caſe ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall refuſe or neglect to finde ſuch ſufficient Sureties, then to ſend ſuch perſon or perſons to the Common Goal, there to remain untill he or they ſhall finde Sureties as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That at ſuch General Seſſions for the Peace, to be held within ſuch County, City, Burrough, or Town Corporate as aforeſaid, ſuch perſon or perſons, ſhall be Indicted for ſo living at high Rates and great Expences, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no viſible Eſtate, Profeſſion, or Calling an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable thereunto, upon which Indictment if he or they ſhall be legally convicted of the ſaid Offence or Offences, then every ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall be ſent to the houſe of Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there to be puniſhed and ſet on work accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law, and there to continue for the ſpace of three moneths; And if ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall be convicted as aforeſaid a ſecond time for the like Offence, then ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſhall be committed to the houſe of Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there to be puniſhed and ſet on work, and there to continue untill he or they ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by the Iuſtices in open Seſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169285:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That if any perſon or perſons, at any time after the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred fifty and ſeven, ſhall, (by playing at Cards, Dice, Tables, Tennis, Bowles, or Shovelboard, Cockfighting, or by Horſe-races, or any Game or Games, or by bearing any part in the Adventure, or by betting on the ſides or hands of ſuch as do or ſhall play as aforeſaid) directly or indirectly, win or gain unto him or themſelves, any ſum or ſums of money, or other thing valuable whatſoever, That then every perſon and perſons, ſo winning or gaining as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſhall forfeit double the ſum or value ſo won or gained; One Moyty thereof to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the other Moyty unto the perſon or perſons who ſhall loſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſo as ſuch loſer do or ſhall proſecute or ſue for the ſame within three Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths next after ſuch Forfeiture; And in default of ſuch proſecution, the ſaid other Moyty to ſuch perſon or perſons who ſhall or will proſecute or ſue for the ſame at anytime within ſix Moneths next after the ſaid three Moneths expired.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That the ſeveral Forfeitures in this Act before mentioned, ſhall or may be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in any of the four Courts of Record at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> wherein no Eſſoign or Wager of Law ſhall be allowed: And that all and every ſuch Plaintiffe or Plaintiffs, Informer or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, ſhall in every ſuch Suit, recover his or their double Coſts; Any Law or Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authority
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169285:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->
aforeſaid, that all Iudgements, Statutes, Recognizances, Mortgages, Bonds, Bills, Promiſes, Covenants, Decrees and other Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances and Engagements whatſoever, that any time, ſince the four and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year One thouſand ſix hundred fourty ſeven, have been, or ſhall hereafter know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly be obtained by, or otherwiſe Made, Given, Acknowledged, or Entred into, to any Scrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or Scriveners, or to any other Perſon or Perſons, for ſecurity, or in ſatisfaction of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or other things, ſince the time aforeſaid, Plaid for, or hereafter to be Plaid for, or Loſt at Cards, Dice, Tables, Tennis, Bowles, Shovel-board, or by Cock-fighting, or by Horſe-races, or by any Game or Games, or by bearing any part in the Adventure, or by Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the ſides or hands of ſuch as Do or ſhall Play as aforeſaid, ſhall be utterly void and of none effect.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and <hi>John Field,</hi> Printers to His Highneſs. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
